<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE Book SYSTEM "gapdoc.dtd"
[<!ENTITY automata "<Alt Not='Text'><URL
Text='Automata'>https://gap-packages.github.io/automata/</URL></Alt><Alt Only='Text'><Package>Automata</Package></Alt>">]
>

<?LaTeX ExtraPreamble="\usepackage{graphicx}"?>
<!-- Documentation to the Automata package. -->

<Book Name="Automata"> 

<TitlePage>
  <Title>
    &automata;
  </Title>
  <Subtitle>
    A package on automata
  </Subtitle>
  <Version> Version <#Include SYSTEM "../version">
  </Version>
  <Author>
    Manuel Delgado<Alt Only="LaTeX"><Br/></Alt>
<Address>
Departamento de Matemática - Faculdade de Ciências<Br/>
Porto<Br/>
Portugal<Br/>
</Address>
<Email>mdelgado@fc.up.pt</Email>
<Homepage>http://www.fc.up.pt/cmup/mdelgado/</Homepage>

  </Author>
  <Author>
    Steve Linton<Alt Only="LaTeX"><Br/></Alt>
<Address>
School of Computer Science<Br/>
University of St Andrews<Br/>
Jack Cole Building, North Haugh<Br/>
St Andrews, Fife, KY16 9SX<Br/>
United Kingdom<Br/>
</Address>
<Email>steve.linton@st-andrews.ac.uk</Email>
<Homepage>http://www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk/~sal/</Homepage>

  </Author>
  <Author>
    José João Morais<Alt Only="LaTeX"><Br/></Alt>
<Address>
No address known<Br/>
</Address>

  </Author>
  <Copyright>
    
&copyright; 2004 by Manuel Delgado, Steve Linton and José Morais <P/>
      <Alt Only="LaTeX">\noindent</Alt> &automata; package is free software; 
      you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the 
      <URL Text="GNU General Public License">http://www.fsf.org/licenses/gpl.html</URL> 
      as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the
      License, or (at your option) any later version. For details, see the file 'GPL' included in the package or see the FSF's own site.
  </Copyright>
  <Acknowledgements>
    
The first author wishes to acknowledge Cyril Nicaud and Paulo Varandas for
their help in programming some functions of the very first version of this
package. He wishes also to acknowledge useful discussions and comments by
Cyril Nicaud, Vítor H. Fernandes, Jean-Eric Pin and Jorge Almeida.
<P/>
The first author also acknowledges support of FCT through CMUP
and the FCT and POCTI Project POCTI/32817/MAT/2000 which is funded in
cooperation with the European Community Fund FEDER.
<P/>
The third author acknowledges financial support of FCT and the POCTI program
through a scholarship given by Centro de Matemática da Universidade do Porto.
<P/>

The authors would like to thank Mark Kambites for his contribution in finding
bugs and making suggestions for the improvement of this package.
<P/>
<P/>
<P/>
Concerning the maintenance:
<P/>
<P/>
The first author was/is (partially) supported by:
<P/> the Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia (FCT) project PTDC/MAT/65481/2006;
<P/> the <E>Centro de Matemática da Universidade do Porto</E> (CMUP), in particular for those periods in which CMUP was funded by
<P/> the European Regional Development Fund through the
program COMPETE and by the Portuguese Government through the FCT - Fundação
para a Ciência e a Tecnologia under the project PEst-C/MAT/UI0144/2011;
<P/> FCT (Portugal) with national (MEC) and European structural funds through the programs FEDER, under the partnership agreement PT2020, under the project UID/MAT/00144/2013.

  </Acknowledgements>
  
  <Colophon>
    
This work started in 1998, when the first author was in the
LIAFA at the University of Paris 7, in a post-doc.
Encouraged by J. E. Pin, he began the implementation in &GAP;3 of
an algorithm obtained some time before to answer a question from the realm
of Finite Semigroups proposed by J. Almeida.<P/>

The first version of this package on automata was prepared by the first author
who gave it the form of a &GAP; share package.
In a second version, prepared by the first and third authors,
many functions have been added and the performance of many of the existing
ones has been improved. Further important improvements, specially concerning performance,
have been achieved when the second author joined the group.

The first author is particularly grateful to Max Horn whose help made the release of Version 1.14 a lot easier. 
<P/>
<P/>
Since Version 1.12, the package is maintained by the first two authors.

Bug reports, suggestions and comments are, of course, welcome. Please use our
email addresses to this effect.

  </Colophon>
  
</TitlePage>

<TableOfContents/>

<Body>

<#Include SYSTEM "introduction.xml">
<#Include SYSTEM "automata.xml">
<#Include SYSTEM "rational.xml">
<#Include SYSTEM "aut-vs-rat.xml">
<#Include SYSTEM "aut-func.xml">
<#Include SYSTEM "finitelang.xml">

</Body>

<#Include SYSTEM "graphs.xml">
<#Include SYSTEM "drawing.xml">
<#Include SYSTEM "foldings.xml">



<Bibliography Databases="AutMan" />

<TheIndex/>

</Book>

<!-- ==================================================================== -->
